Guide to the Pittsburgh Savoyards Records, 1939-1974 CTC.1974.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Savoyards Records
1939-1975
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Savoyards
CTC.1974.01
3 Linear Feet
The Pittsburgh Savoyards Records document a theatre company that began in 1938 and have continually performed Gilbert & Sullivan comic operas since that year. The materials in this collection include programs, photos, scrapbooks, clippings, and newsletters.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Pittsburgh Savoyards in 1974.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following seven series:
Series I. Constitution
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Programs
Series IV. Publicity and Newspaper Clippings
Series V. Photographs
Series VI. Scrapbooks and Ephemera
Series VII. Oversize Materials
Scope and Content Notes
The Pittsburgh Savoyards Records are incomplete, and for the most part, constitute memorabilia. Programs and photographs (1939-1974) are the most extensive for the 1940's and 1950's. Eight scrapbooks, containing chiefly newspaper clippings, some programs, issues of the company newsletter, and miscellany, cover between 1939-1951 and 1964-1980 in great detail; additional clippings cover between 1946-1962. A small amount of correspondence is chiefly personal. Other items of note include the organization's constitution (probable date of 1973), new releases, and five libretti. A few items from the Curtis Collection's Pittsburgh vertical files were integrated with the Savoyards Records.
History
Established in 1938, the Pittsburgh Savoyards is the fourth oldest Gilbert and Sullivan Company in the United States. Its origins are described in a tenth anniversary program: "In the fall of 1938 the adult choirs of Calvary Episcopal Church and their friends began rehearsal of Gilbert and Sullivan's 'Pirates of Penzance' as a choir camp benefit. Directors were George M. Rowland, Jr. and the late Dr. Harvey Gaul, then organist and choirmaster of Calvary Church. In May 1939 after a successful two-night run of 'The Pirates' company. The group's purpose was to produce Gilbert and Sullivan and other light operas on a non-profit basis for the enjoyment and education of the membership."
Since 1938-1939, the Pittsburgh Savoyards has presented several Gilbert and Sullivan operas each season, performing in various local theatres and auditoriums. Other works presented infrequently are The Devil and Daniel Webster, Die Fledermaus, and Amahl and the Night Visitors. The Savoyards have also sung occasionally at concerts and as an opera chorus.
Burt Mustin, a native Pittsburgher who was later to achieve fame as an actor in national television situation comedies, was active in the organization in the 1940's, singing such roles as the Judge in Trial by Jury, Poo-Bah in The Mikado, and Sir Joseph Porter in H.M.S. Pinafore.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Savoyards Records, 1939-1975, CTC.1974.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh Savoyards Records, 1939-1975, CTC.08, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Theatrical companies -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Operetta -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Performing arts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Scrapbooks; Clippings (Information artifacts); Photographs; Theater programs; Correspondence; Newsletters; Press releases; Constitutions; Choruses; Musical theater -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Sullivan, Arthur; Gilbert, W. S. (William Schwenck); Pittsburgh Savoyards
- Constitution, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series is comprised of one folder that contains the constitution and by-laws of the Pittsburgh Savoyards, Incorporated. The document is seven pages long and is undated; a note on the last page that states that "this printing of the Constitution and By-Laws incorporates the Amendments approved by the general membership at the Annual Meeting of May 29, 1973."
  - Constitution of the Pittsburgh Savoyards Inc. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1945-1972; II.
  In this series are two folders of letters from Savoyards and their friends who served in World War II. There is also a folder of miscellaneous correspondence, chiefly thank you notes.
  - World War II service letters, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1945-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Programs, 1940-1974; III.
  The programs in this series are filed in chronological order with some gaps. A few of the missing programs can be found in the scrapbooks.
  - Programs, 1940-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5-16)
- Publicity and Newspaper Clippings, 1946-1973; IV.
  Within this series are news releases, flyers, and three issues of This Week in Pittsburgh. The newspaper clippings (mostly reviews and publicity) are arranged chronologically and date between 1946 and 1962.
  - News releases and flyers (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - This Week in Pittsburgh, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1946-1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photographs, 1939-1975; V.
  The photographs are filed alphabetically covering Savoyards history between 1939-1974, but most complete for the 1940's and 1950's. There are also rehearsal pictures and portraits, the latter filed by person's name.
  - Amahl and the Night Visitors, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Concerts - Schenley Hotel lawn (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cox and Box, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Devil and Daniel Webster, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gondoliers, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gondoliers, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gondoliers, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Iolanthe, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Iolanthe, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Iolanthe, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mikado, 1943-1952 (Box 2, Folder 11-15)
  - Mikado (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Patience, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Patience, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Patience, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - H.M.S. Pinafore, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - H.M.S. Pinafore, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - H.M.S. Pinafore, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - H.M.S. Pinafore, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - H.M.S. Pinafore, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - H.M.S. Pinafore, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pirates of Penzance, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Pirates of Penzance, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pirates of Penzance, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pirates of Penzance, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pirates of Penzance - no dates (Box 3, Folder 8-13)
  - Princess Ida, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Rosalinda, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Ruddigore, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Ruddigore, 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
  - Ruddigore, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Sorcerer, 1941-1948 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Sorcerer, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sorcerer, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Trial by Jury, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Trial by Jury, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Yeoman of the Guard, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Yeoman of the Guard, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Rehearsal - Unidentified production (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Portraits - Identified A-Z (Box 4, Folder 11-16)
  - Portraits - Unidentified (Box 4, Folder 17-19)
  - Negatives (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 1939-1969; VI.
  Most of the scrapbooks have been taken apart and placed in folders. They contain miscellaneous material, chief-reviews and publicity, also some programs, issues of the organizations newsletter, etc. The libretti titles are Ruddigore, H.M.S. Pinafore, The Sorcerer, Iolanthe, and Yeomen of the Guard. Four are printed; the last is mimeographed and only one is dated.
  - Yeomen of the Guard scrapbook, 1939-1945 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
  - Loose material from Yeomen of the Guard scrapbook, 1939-1945 (Box 5, Folder 9-12)
  - "Miscellany" scrapbook, 1940-1943 (Box 5, Folder 13-15)
  - "Miscellany" scrapbook, 1940-1943 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1945-1948 (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Scrapbook, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1964-1969 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - Posters - Princess Ida and Mikado, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Arthur Sullivan's Vocal Album book (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Libretti (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Post office permits, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera, 1945-1963 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Oversize Material, VII.
  - Enlarged photographs and Mikado poster, 1946 (Map-case 1, Drawer 4)